Alright, the last section of this chapter deals with lower urinary tract carcinoma.
So the lower urinary tract includes the renal pelvis, the ureter, the bladder, and the urethra.
And there are three types of cancers that classically arise from this location.
The first is urothelial carcinoma, the second is squamous cell carcinoma, and the third is adenocarcinoma.
Now as far as urothelial carcinoma is concerned,
this is a malignant tumor that arises from the urothelial lining of the lower urinary tract.
So the pelvis, the ureter, the bladder, or the urethra.
Now remember that the normal lining of the entire lower urinary tract is actually urothelial.
And so therefore, this is the most common type of lower urinary tract cancer.
The most common location within the lower tract is going to be the bladder.
The number one risk factor for urothelial carcinoma is cigarette smoke.
In particular, within cigarette smoke, polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons.
Additionally, naphthalamine is a risk factor.
Naphthalamine actually is one of the carcinogens present in cigarette smoke.
And so therefore, it's just a further reminder that cigarette smoke is a major risk factor.
Azo dyes are an important risk factor.
These are used for coloring.
For example, there was a study which showed that there was an increased incidence of urothelial carcinoma
in hairdressers in Los Angeles.
And of course, hairdressers were using dyes to color the hair of their clients.
And so azo dyes increases the risk as well.
And then finally, long-term cyclophosphamide can increase the risk for urothelial carcinoma,
as can finacetin.
And so these are two important high-yield associations to be aware of as well.
Urothelial carcinoma is generally seen in older adults.
The classic presentation is painless hematuria.
And it's important to note that it arises via two distinct pathways.
And this is particularly high-yield.
In the papillary pathway, tumors develop as papillary growths.
And remember that a papillary growth is essentially a fibrovascular core
with a blood vessel running through it upon which epithelium is placed.
And so this would be the papillary pattern of urothelial carcinoma.
Now, important to note that in the papillary pathway,
the tumors start as low-grade and then progress to high-grade,
and then eventually they invade.
And so this is the classic progression of the papillary pathway.
The second pathway is called the flat pathway.
And in this particular pathway, you develop high-grade urothelial carcinoma
that develops as a flat lesion.
Now, important to note that this tumor does not start low-grade,
but starts as a high-grade tumor that eventually progresses to invade.
So again, the papillary pathway begins as a low-grade tumor
that progresses to high-grade and then invades.
And the flat pathway begins as high-grade and then eventually invades.
Another important thing to note about the flat pathway
is that it is associated with early P53 mutations,
and that is particularly high-yield.
Again, early P53 mutations in the flat pathway.
Here's an image of the flat pathway,
and you can clearly see here's a lamina propria.
This epithelium is sitting on a basement membrane,
and that this lesion appears flat but high-grade.
And here's a picture of the papillary pathway
where you can clearly see that you've got these blood vessels
with fibrous tissues sitting in the middle of these finger-like projections.
Here's a classic picture of a finger-like projection.
And again, this papillary pathway begins as low-grade,
then eventually progresses to high-grade,
and then eventually invades.
Now, patients who develop urothelial carcinoma
often have multifocal tumors and often show recurrence.
And the reason is that the entire urothelial surface
is actually mutated in a phenomenon known as the field defect.
Now, here the idea is that the entire urothelium
has been hit with carcinogens over a long period of time,
especially in a person who smokes.
And so the entire field, all of the urothelial surface,
is essentially mutated.
And it's only a matter of time before multiple tumors develop.
And so patients often have multiple tumors,
and they often have recurrence
because there are so many mutations
lining the surface of that urothelium.
Again, that's called a field defect.
The second type of tumor that can arise
from the lower urinary tract is squamous cell carcinoma.
Of course, this is a malignant proliferation of squamous cells,
and it usually involves the bladder.
Now, remember that the lower urinary tract
does not normally have any squamous epithelium.
And therefore, in order to form a squamous cell carcinoma,
you must first develop squamous metoplasia.
Of course, that metoplasia would eventually become dysplasia,
and the dysplasia would eventually become squamous cell carcinoma.
The key risk factors for squamous cell carcinoma are chronic cystitis.
Chronic inflammation can result in squamous metoplasia,
which can then eventually progress to cancer.
One very high-yield risk factor is schistosoma hematobium infection.
This is classically seen in the Middle East,
and on board exams, it's classically seen in a Middle Eastern male,
particularly a young Middle Eastern male.
And so what happens in this particular case
is that the schistosoma hematobium embeds itself within the bladder wall.
That results in chronic inflammation,
and again, that chronic inflammation results in a squamous metoplasia,
which then eventually progresses to squamous cell carcinoma.
Another risk factor would be long-standing nephrolithiasis.
And again, the same idea here
is that with a chronic irritation of the urothelium,
you develop a squamous metoplasia,
and the squamous metoplasia eventually becomes cancer.
The third type of lower urinary tract carcinoma
is adenocarcinoma.
This is, of course, a malignant proliferation of glands,
and it usually involves the bladder.
Now, it's important to note
that you normally don't have glandular epithelium lining the bladder,
and so therefore, this is only going to arise in particular circumstances.
One super high-yield circumstance
is that this can arise from a urachal remnant.
Now, this is high-yield because it ties back into embryology.
So let's just remind ourselves that the urachis is a duct
that connects the fetal bladder with the yolk sac,
and, of course, it allows the bladder to drain waste into the yolk sac.
Now, normally, this would run from the dome of the bladder
through the umbilical cord,
and it is lined by glandular cells.
If there's failure to involute the urachis such that there's a remnant,
this remnant can actually then become adenocarcinoma.
And it's important to note, for board examination purposes,
that this adenocarcinoma would be present at the dome of the bladder.
Again, high-yield adenocarcinoma that arises from a urachal remnant
would be present at the dome of the bladder.
Another risk factor for the development of adenocarcinoma
would be cystitis glandularis.
This is where a patient has chronic inflammation of the bladder
and gets a columnar metaplasia in response to that chronic inflammation.
Of course, that columnar metaplasia could then become adenocarcinoma.
Now, the final association with adenocarcinoma is bladder extrophy.
In bladder extrophy, you get a congenital failure to form the caudal
or the lower portion of the anterior abdominal and bladder walls.
And when this occurs, this exposes the surface of the bladder
to the outside world, which then increases the risk in the future
of development of an adenocarcinoma.
And that concludes both the section as well as the chapter.